A cat has had her litter,
一只貓生了一窩幼崽
here, in my rooms.
就在我的房間這里
Look at it!
瞧你喲!
Black as the devil,
漆黑如惡魔撒旦
born right here, under my very bed.
就在我的床下 它出世了
How's that for a bad omen before a journey?
你說這是不是我們這次遠行的兇兆呢?
You shouldn't leave.
您不應該離開
Merry Thomas, when Norfolk threatens to bite...
托馬斯 當諾爾福克威脅說要撕碎我的時候...
.. it's time to be gone.
也由不得我不離開了
You won't like the north.
您是不會喜愛北方的
I am the Archbishop of York.
我可是約克的大主教
Yes, but you've never been. I have.
雖如此 但您從未到過北方 而我去過
Filthy weather, people, morals.
那里民風彪悍 荒蠻未開
The King wants me gone.
但國王想要我遠離啊
He wants to humiliate me.
他想讓我蒙羞
Thinks it sends a sharp message to the Pope.
也覺得這算是給羅馬教皇一個警告
I feel like Katherine...
我就像凱瑟琳王后一樣...
.. cast off.
被罷黜了
But still, I love him.
但依然敬愛他
What will we do?
我們還能做什么呢?
Bribe people.
收買人心
You still have land.
您還有土地
Even if the King takes everything you have, people will ask themselves,
即使國王查抄了您的全部身家 百姓仍會自問
"Can he truly give what belongs to the church?"
"他真的會輕易將教會的所屬物交出嗎？"
No-one will be sure of their title unless you confirm it.
除非是經過您的首肯 不然他們的頭銜也名不正言不順
So you see, my Lord, you still...
所以主人您仍然...
- You still have cards in your hand. - Yes.
- 您仍然有王牌在手  - 確實如此
And after all...
但是 說起來...
.. if he wants to bring a treason...
欲加之罪 何患無辭...
If the King meant to charge you with treason,
如果國王意欲將叛國罪強加于您
- you'd be in the tower now, wouldn't you?       - Yes.
- 您現在怕是早已在象牙塔里了 不是嗎?  - 沒錯
He misses you.
國王仍牽掛您
You'll return to favour.
您會重獲圣寵的
New life,
一條新生命
born under your very bed?
誕生在您的床下
Well... I'd read that as a good omen.
要我說 這是大吉之兆
Ah, you lawyer.
呵呵 真是巧舌如簧呢
Look who's back for Christmas.
看看誰在圣誕節歸來了
What's this, Gregory,some kind of beard?
這是什么 格雷戈里 總算長胡子了？
Think I've seen more hair on a side of bacon.
我在培根的反面 可見過更多的毛
Gregory says we can race his dogs up and down the hall.
格雷戈里說我們能在大廳里遛狗
- Father.   - Welcome home, Gregory.
- 父親大人  - 歡迎回家 格雷戈里
That was a calculation.
那是設計完美的棋局
It wasn't just where I dropped them.
可不是隨意擺的
Sorry.
對不起
Do you remember that one Christmas
您還記得有一年圣誕節
when we had the giant in the pageant?
我們的露天晚會上見到了一個巨人嗎
Here in the parish? I do.
在教區里 我記得
"I am a giant."
"我是個巨人"
"My name is Marlinspike."
"我叫馬林斯派克"
Aunt Johane says we won't have the Epiphany Feast this year.
約翰娜姑母說我們今年不舉辦主顯節宴會了
We can't.
沒辦法
No-one would come.
沒人會赴約的
Because of the Cardinal's disgrace?
因為大主教被罷黜了?
People in Cambridge are laughing at my greyhounds.
劍橋的那幫書呆子笑話我的靈緹犬
Why?
為什么?
Because they're black.
因為它們是黑色的
They should be white.
但它們本應是白色的
They say, "Only felons have dogs that you can't see at night."
他們說 "只有惡霸才會養能在夜里潛行的黑土狗"
Aha.
呵呵
Look.
聽著
"I am a giant.
"我是個巨人"
"My name is Marlinspike."
"我的名字是馬林斯派克"
"Grrrr!"
"額啊啊啊啊啊！"
The dogs will kill it.
我的狗會傷害這貓的
Do you think he's afraid of me?
你覺得他怕我么?
Why should he be?
為什么要怕你?
I don't know.
我不清楚
With everybody else,he seems so lively...
和其他人在一起的時候 他看起來很活躍...
but when he sees me...
而當他看見我的時候...
You're a kind father.
你是個慈愛的父親
Too much so, I think. You spoil him.
也許有點太過溺愛 都慣壞了他
That's what Liz always said.
莉茲也經常這么說
Liz and I had nothing when we were girls.
當莉茲和我還是小女孩的時候 我們一無所有
Not a comb. Never had a mirror.
沒有梳子 更別提鏡子
I remember when he was a baby and I used to warm his shirt
我記得他還只是一個襁褓中的嬰兒時
for him in front of the fire.
我經常拿著他的襯衣站在火爐旁烤暖和
Liz would say "Don't do that. He'll expect it every day."
莉茲會跟我說 "別這樣 他都被你寵壞了"
Seems such a long time since there was a baby in the house.
屋里有個嬰兒哭鬧的日子是一去不復返了
Don't look at me.
別盯著我看
Does John Williamson not do his duty by you?
難道約翰 威廉姆森沒有同你行夫妻之事嗎?
His duty's not my pleasure.
和他同房非我所愿
There's a conversation I shouldn't have had.
真不該嘴賤提這事
Wriothesley.
我是里奧斯利
It's spelled W-R-I-O-T- ...
應該這么拼...
Just call me Risley.
呃...叫我里斯利就好
Master Risley, we're always looking for bright young men.
里斯利學士 我們一直在找前途光明的小伙子
-You worked for the Cardinal, I think? -Yes, sir.
- 你曾替主教效過力吧？ - 是的 先生
But then left with Stephen Gardiner?
但又去跟了史蒂芬 伽迪納？
I'm his clerk.
只是幫他管帳而已
But it doesn't occupy all my time
并不占用我的全部時間
and I'm keen to learn something of business, sir.
我一直想有機會能學習經商之道 先生
Oh, we're all business here at Austin Friars... aren't we, boys?
呵呵 我們奧斯汀兄弟會 一直都忙著做買賣 是不 孩子們
You know Gardiner will have sent him here to spy on us.
你早知道伽迪納 會派他來監視我們的吧
Well, he seems obliging.
他看起來還挺有禮貌的
Perhaps we could send him back to spy on Gardiner.
也許我們可以試試反間計
How's he been?
他怎么樣了
He's whipping himself?
他一直在鞭笞自己？
The monks who come to him brought it.
幾個修道士給他的
Body of Christ.
我的上帝啊！
Who makes these things?
這些到底是誰做的
Who ties a thorn to horse hair?
能將荊棘和馬鬃系在一起
People ought to be found better jobs.
做這玩意兒真是太屈才了
That settles it, we have to get him out of here.
決定了 我們要趕緊帶他離開這
Oh, oh, God.
天吶
He'd be better off in Yorkshire.
在約克郡他的處境會好很多
But how would we pay for it?
但我們會承受什么代價呢
If only you would see the King...
不過要是你能見到國王...
Take a message for me to Wolsey, will you?
幫我傳個口信給沃爾西 好嗎
There's a Breton merchant who's complaining that his ship
有個布里多尼[法國地名]的商人抱怨說 八年前他的船
was seized eight years ago and he still hasn't received compensation.
被沒收了 至今尚未得到賠償
No-one can find the paper work.
當時的筆錄文件找不到了
The Cardinal would have handled the case.
我記得這是主教當時負責的案子
- Do you think he'll remember it?  - I'm sure he will.
- 你覺得他還記得嗎   - 他一定記得
That'll be the one with powdered pearls for ballast
應該是那艘艙室中滿載著
and unicorns' horns in its hold.
珍珠粉還藏有獨角獸角的船
Yes, that'll be the one.
是 就是那艘船
If the case is in doubt, sir, may I look into it?
陛下 如果這件案子有疑點的話 我可以跟進案情嗎
I don't think you have a locus standi in the matter.
我不認為你有這個資格
God, let him, Harry.
亨利 讓他去吧
By the time this fellow's finished, the Breton'll be paying you.
等這家伙結案了 那個布里多尼人可還要付大筆酬謝費的
I'll say this for you.
說些為你好的話
You stick by your man.
你是主教的附屬品
I never had anything but kindness from the Cardinal.
除了主教的恩情 我一無所有
You have no other master?
你沒有別的依靠了？
1,000 pounds?
一千英鎊?
Don't tell anyone.
不要說出去
It's the best I can do.
我只能幫到這兒了
Take it with my blessing.
接受我的好意去吧
And ask him to pray for me.
也請他為我祈禱
Every day, I miss the Cardinal of York.
我無時無刻不在想念著約克大主教
Oh, it's only a tenth of what he's owed the Cardinal for over a decade.
噢 比起過去十年他虧欠主教的 還不到九牛一毛
And not so much when you have a cardinal to move.
花這點錢就罷黜了一個紅衣主教 對他很值了
How much of your own money will you put into this?
你自己又倒貼了多少進去呢
Some debts are not to be reckoned.
帳不是這么算的
I heard a rumour recently about someone you know.
我最近倒是聽到了關于某個你認識的人的流言
Thomas Wyatt.
托馬斯 懷特
Wyatt and the Lady Anne.
懷特和安妮夫人
It's an old story.
老生常談了
If it's such an old story, why hasn't the King heard it?
老生常談嗎 那國王怎么從未聽過這個故事?
Part of the art of ruling, perhaps. Know when to shut your ears.
也許經國治世之道 就是明白何時充耳不聞
Aren't the English odd?
英國人可真是奇怪
Christ, aren't they?!
誰說不是呢
Hmm.
哈
But you understand, I think?
不過你是懂的吧？
She interests you?
她對你感興趣
A world where Anne can be queen
一個安妮都能成為王后的混亂世界里
is a world where Cromwell can be...?
那克倫威爾能成為...？
Hendon and Royston, Huntingdon, Peterborough.
亨頓和羅伊斯頓 亨廷頓 彼得伯勒（英國東部城市）
I've sent riders on ahead so everything will be ready for you.
我已經讓車馬輜重現行 一切都會為你打點好的
This is a tactical retreat.
這只是戰術性撤退
Not a surrender.
并不是投降
Lady Anne is the key to winning back Henry.
想贏回亨利的重用 安妮夫人才是關鍵
Mm-hm..
嗯..
Find a way into her confidence, Tom.
湯姆 你要想辦法贏得她的信任
Work a device to please her.
想辦法哄她開心
The only way to please that lady is to crown her Queen of England.
唯一能讓安妮夫人開心的辦法 就是為她戴上英格蘭王后的寶冠
- Will you come north?  - Mm-hm.
- 你會到北邊來嗎？ - 嗯哼
I'll come and fetch you, as soon as he summons you back. And he will.
只要國王傳召您回來 我會親身去接您回來 他一定會的
God bless you...
上帝保佑你...
mine own entirely beloved Cromwell.
我摯愛的克倫威爾
Thomas?
托馬斯？
Oh, er, when I'm gone.
我離開之后再看
I want the whole of the Archbishop's palace scrubbed out.
把主教宮殿里的所有東西都搬走
My lord will be bringing his own bed.
大人只習慣睡自己的床
Draft in kitchen staff from the King's Arms.
廚房員工從國王近侍中挑選
I think I should go myself.
算了 還是我親自去吧
No, we can do it.
不不 我們可以做好的
Well, check... Can you take this?
好吧 檢查...幫我拿一下
Check the stabling.
去檢查下馬廄
And get in musicians.
再請些樂師來
Last time I passed through, there were some pigsties
上次我經過時 那還有些柴垛還是豬圈什么的
or something against the palace wall.
還有一些不應該存在于宮殿之內的東西
- Find the owner, pay him off, knock 'em down.  -Sir...
- 看看是誰的 打點一下 全部清除   - 先生...
It's time to let the cardinal go.
是時候讓主教離開了
You know the first time we met,
記得我們初次見面時
was when you were a young student.
你還是個年輕的學生
- Where was this?  - Lambeth Palace.
- 在哪來著？ - 蘭貝斯宮
My uncle John was the cook there
我叔叔約翰 曾是那里的廚師
and I worked some days in the kitchens.
我在那兒也做過幾天幫工
I served you once.
有一次是為你服務的
I don't think so.
我都沒什么印象了
I remember, one evening we were playing football
我記得有天晚上 我們在踢球
and I heard a recorder playing...
突然 我聽到有人在演奏豎笛...
Ah, my other guest...
我的另一位客人
Now, you carry on...
你先抱著...
Now, Henry, leave Master Gardiner alone.
亨利 別打擾伽迪納大人
You come along to the house. Come on, come on.
跟我回屋里面去 走吧 快點
Let's go, let's go to the house.
走吧 快進屋里
There.
好了好了
About Master Wriothesley...
關于里奧斯利學士...
And a good evening to you, Stephen.
也祝你晚上好 史蒂芬
Remind me, is he working for me, or for you?
跟我提個醒 他是為我干活還是你?
For you, I would have thought?
我覺得他是你的人
Then why is he always at your house?
那他為什么總在你家出沒?
Well, he's not a bound apprentice.
他又不是學徒
He can come and go as he pleases.
他想來就來 想走就走
He thinks he'll make his fortune, I suppose.
我猜他想發大財
Everyone knows money sticks to your hands.
大家都知道你富甲一方
He wants to know what he can learn from...
他想從你這個...不管你怎么稱呼自己...
whatever it is you call yourself these days.
學到點小花招
A person.
我只是一個普通人而已
The Duke of Norfolk says I'm a person.
諾爾福克公爵說我只是一個普通人
Is that his fool?
那個就是他的傻兒子嗎?
He's supposed to have fallen off a church roof and landed on his head.
他本該是從教堂屋頂摔下來 頭先著地
- Supposed to?  - It would be just like More to keep a fool who wasn't.
- "本該是"?  – 如果那件事不是意外的話 就更讓人糟心了
Just to embarrass people.
只會讓人愈加尷尬
Henry Pattinson is excitable tonight.
亨利 帕丁森 今晚好像特別激動呢
I hope his diet has not been too rich.
希望他吃的別那么油膩
No anxieties on that score...
我就不擔心油膩的問題...
Tyndale has been sighted in Hamburg, they say.
他們說汀代爾在漢堡[德國城市]一直在被監視著
You'd know him, if you saw him, I suppose?
如果你看到他 你能認出來吧
So would you, I suppose?
你也一樣吧
I hope to get the means to proceed against him
我希望能找到個辦法對付他
for sedition in his writing.
針對他書里的那些反叛言論
Have you found sedition in Tyndale's writing?
你真的在汀代爾的書中看到了反叛言論嗎
Very good.
很好
You hear that, Stephen?
你聽見了嗎 史蒂芬
A lesser lawyer would have said, "I have read Tyndale,
無名小律師才會說 "我讀了汀代爾的書
"and I find no fault there."
沒發現什么不對勁的地方呀"
But Thomas will not be tripped, will he?
但托馬斯可沒有這么好騙哦
Well, I admit, I have read Tyndale.
我承認 我讀過汀代爾的書
I have picked apart his so-called translations.
還逐字推敲了他那所謂的譯文
I have also read Luther.
我也讀過路德的書[馬丁 路德 德國基督神學家]
You have such a pretty way with Latin.
你的拉丁語說的非常優雅
So, "He that toucheth pitch shall be defiled."
那么 "近墨者黑"
Unless his name is Thomas More.
除非此人是托馬斯 莫爾
There you are, Wolsey always told me you were a man of the Bible.
呵 沃爾西總說你是《圣經》的狂熱崇拜者
Thomas Cromwell, why don't you marry again?
托馬斯 克倫威爾 你為什么沒有再娶妻了呢
No-one will have me, Lady Alice.
沒人看得上我 愛麗絲夫人
Nonsense. Your master may be down, but you're not poor.
胡說 你的主人也許是垮臺了 但你并不窮啊
And you've got everything below in good working order, haven't you?
而且你的一切現在都還算井然有序 不是嗎
Alice! What have I told you about drinking wine?
愛麗絲! 我跟你說喝酒時要注意什么來著?
Your nose is glowing!
你都喝的紅光滿面了!
Why am I bringing you to Westminster?
我為什么要帶你去威斯敏斯特來著
I'm off to see Lady Anne.
我要去見安妮夫人
You didn't say so.
你之前可沒這么說
I can't tell you all my plans, Stephen.
我不會把所有計劃都告訴你的 史蒂芬
What would young Wriothesley have to do, then?
不然年輕的里奧謝思利 可就沒事做了
Oh, dear God, I'm starving!
噢 天哪 我要餓死了!
I wish I'd lain hands on the white rabbit, I'd eat it raw.
真希望那小白兔還在 我就能把它生吞活剝了
Did you know that More goes to bed at nine o'clock every night?
你知道莫爾每晚九點準時入睡嗎
With Alice?
和愛麗絲一起?
Apparently not.
當然不是
Don't you ever think of getting married, Stephen?
你從未想過結婚嗎 史蒂芬
I'm in holy orders.
我是神職人員
Oh, come on. You must have women.
得了吧 你肯定有女人的
Don't you?
沒有過？！
What kind of a... Putney enquiry is that?!
你這簡直是個毫無意義的反問！
Ah, it's you.
啊 是你
I like your... grey velvet.
我喜歡你這身...灰色天鵝絨
Where did you get it?
你在哪買的?
Italy.
意大利
Can you get me some?
能給我買點嗎?
It's been so long since I had new clothes.
我很久沒有新衣服了
If you're waiting for HER, I should warn you, she's in a temper.
如果你是在等她 我得提醒你 她正在大發雷霆
- Ah-ha.  - Nothing happens quickly enough for Anne.
- 啊哈  –安妮嫌她上位的速度太慢了
You'd think she'd be happy.
你覺得她會開心
You know, when the king first turned his attention to her, he thought,
你知道 當國王第一次注意到她時 國王想的是
knowing how things are done in France,
她既然那么了解法國的那些事
that she might accept a certain... position at court.
那她會接受宮里的一個特定的位置[情婦]
But that wasn't enough for Anne.
但那對安妮來說 卻不知足
You know what she said to me?
你知道她對我說過什么嗎
She said, "This isn't France, and I'm not a fool like you, Mary."
她說 "這不是法國 而我也沒你這么傻 瑪麗"
Hm.
嗯...
Because she...
因為她...
- Because she knows I was Henry's mistress... - Hm.
- 因為她知道我曾是亨利的情婦...  - 嗯...
.. and she sees how I am left. And she takes a lesson from it.
...而且她也見證了我是怎么被拋棄的 她從中吸取了很多教訓
She's vowed that she'll marry him. And what Anne wants, she'll have.
她發誓要嫁給他 而且無論安妮想要什么 她就一定要得到
- And you? - Me?
- 那你呢?  - 我?
I am to be swept out after supper like the old rushes.
我只是一個被人玩弄過拋棄了的女人
My father says I'm a mouth to feed
我父親說我是吃白飯的
and my uncle Norfolk says I'm a whore.
我叔父諾爾福克說我是個賤女人
I need a husband, to stop them calling me names.
我需要丈夫 來阻止他們的那些外號
Well...
要我說的話...
.. you should ask for someone young and handsome.
...你值得找一個年輕有為的英俊丈夫
Don't ask, don't get.
自己不去爭取 怎么能找到如意郎君呢
No, what I want is a husband who upsets them.
不 我想找的是一個能膈應死他們的丈夫
And who won't die.
而且不會因此喪命的丈夫
Don't ask, don't get.
是你說的要爭取 我現在爭取了
They'd kill you.
他們會殺了你的
You're right. They would.
你說的對 他們會的
If she's sent for you,
如果她傳召你
she means to flatter you.
其實她是想討好你
She's going to ask you to do some little thing for her.
她會讓你從些許小事開始幫她的忙
And then she'll make you hers. Take my advice.
然后讓你為她所用 聽我的話
Before she does, turn around and walk the other way.
在她有所行動之前 快逃走吧
Cheer it up, can't you?
弄點歡快的音樂好嘛
What did you just do?
你剛剛做了什么?
I hit Mark Smeaton.
我就碰了馬克 史密頓一下
- But only with one finger. - Who?
- 只用了一根手指而已   - 誰？
Oh. Is that his name?
噢 原來樂師叫這名字
Where've you been?
你去哪了
Utopia.
烏托邦
Oh. What was the talk?
噢 談的怎么樣
The vices and follies of women.
女人的陰暗面
I suppose you joined in?
我想你應該聊的很開心吧
My chaplain. Dr Cranmer.
我的牧師 克萊姆
Hiding. Because there's no good news.
他躲在一邊 因為沒什么好消息
He's just back from Rome.
他剛從羅馬回來
I hear that Rome will issue a decree telling the king to part from me?
我聽說羅馬會頒布教令 要求國王離開我
- That would be a mistake on Rome's part. - Yes, it would.
- 那是羅馬犯的錯   - 必須是的
Because he won't be told.
他也不會聽之任之的
What is he? Some child?
當他是什么了 一小屁孩兒嗎
I've read Tyndale.
我讀過汀代爾的書
The subject must obey his king as he would God.
國民必須絕對服從國王 就如他會聽從上帝一樣
Do I have the sense of it?
你說我理解的準確嗎
The Pope will learn his place.
教皇會清楚他的地位的
Why did you send for me?
您傳召我來什么事呢
I've something to show you...
我有東西給你看...
- Oh, please, don't give it currency...  - Give it!
- 拜托 不要把它... - 拿出來！
This was in my bed.
這在我床上發現的
The sickly milk-faced creeper had turned down the sheet.
那個白臉下人給我換床單的時候發現的
Of course, I can't get any sense out of her,
當然 我從她身上什么也沒問出來
she cries if you look at her sideways,
她連被別人斜眼盯著都受不了
so I don't know who put it there.
所以我不知道是誰把這玩意放在我床上的
That's the Queen, Katherine, you see?
看到了嗎 那是凱瑟琳王后
And that's me.
而這個是我
Anne sans tete.
無頭的安妮
I am told that Wolsey kept you
我總聽說沃爾西之所以留著你
because you always knew the London gossip.
是因為倫敦的八卦消息都逃不出你的耳朵
If you find out who is responsible for this, I want you to tell me.
如果你能查出這事是誰做的 希望你能如實稟告我
I have a new motto. Did you know?
我有了一個新的座右銘 你知道嗎
"Never mind who grudges it, this will happen."
"任誰怨聲載道 我亦一往無前"
I mean to have him.
我注定要得到國王的心
I think this is the one that cries,so don't look at her sideways.
這就是容易被嚇哭的那位 別斜眼盯著她看
-Master Cromwell.-I haven't seen you for a long time.
- 克倫威爾大人 - 好久沒見了
What have you been doing? Where have you been?
你一直都在干嘛 都去哪了
Sewing.
縫紉
Where I'm sent.
在我被遣送的地方
And spying, too, I think?
還有監視別人 對吧
I'm not very good at it. I don't speak French.
我可不擅長監視 而且也不會說法語
So, please, don't you. It gives me nothing to report.
所以您就別拷問我了 我沒什么可報告的
You know Dr Cranmer?
那你認識克萊姆牧師嗎
- No.  - No...
- 不認識  - 不不...
- This is Doctor Cranmer.  - Oh...
- 我是說...這位是克萊姆牧師  - 噢...
Now, you're supposed to say who you are.
現在你該要自報家門了
John Seymour's daughter, from Wolf Hall.
約翰 西摩的女兒 來自狼廳
Well, good luck. I'll try to keep the conversations in English.
祝你好運吧 我盡量只用英語來進行這對話
I would be obliged.
真的萬分感激呢
You're going back to Cambridge now?
你現在要回劍橋嗎
Sadly, not to stay. The Boleyn family likes to have me close.
很遺憾不能久留 博林一家希望我呆在他們身邊
How, erm, how is the Duke of Norfolk?
呃 諾爾福克公爵怎么樣了
He's in a fury.
他正在氣頭上
About what?
為什么
He heard your cardinal has reached Southwell
他聽說紅衣大主教閣下已經到了索斯維爾
and the crowds have come flocking from far and wide just to see him.
人們從各地涌來就為了看他一眼
As if it were a triumphal procession.
簡直像一支凱旋歸來的軍隊
He should... perhaps...
他應該...也許...
be more cautious.
更加小心謹慎點
If the king was offended once,
如果國王能生一次氣
he can be offended again.
就還會有第二次
So, what's she like?
她長什么樣呢
The Lady Anne?
安妮夫人
Tall or short?
高還是矮
Neither.
不高不矮
They say she dances well.
他們說她舞跳得很好
We didn't dance.
我們沒跳過
Are her teeth good?
她牙齒好嗎
When she sinks them into me,
等她用它們咬我的時候
I'll let you know.
我會告訴你的
Sounds like you've got close enough.
似乎你已經靠她很近了
Why does God test us?
為何上帝要如此考驗我們?
I don't think we'll pass.
我也不認為我們能通過考驗
Conditions could be better.
條件還有待提高
Um, he wondered if you could send quails?
他希望你可以送點鵪鶉過去
- The food is deplorable up there.  - I did warn him.
- 那兒的食物太難吃了  - 我提醒過他了
Everywhere he goes, Thomas, they flock to see him.
托馬斯 無論走到哪 人們都蜂擁而來
Thousands of them!
成千上萬的人
You can see his old spirit returning.
他的昔日雄風又回來了
He's called a convocation of the northern church.
他在北部教堂召開了教士會議
Without informing the king?
沒有通知國王嗎
He said, "Ah, George, why do they need to know."
他說 "呵 喬治 他們沒必要知道"
It's a signal of independence, that's all.
這是獨立的信號 沒別的意思
Some might say a signal of pride.
有人會說這是傲慢自負的信號
I know.
我知道
I know what people are saying.
我知道人們在議論什么
That I'm working for myself now,
說我現在一個人單干了
that I've been bought out.
說我被收買了
If you came and spoke to him, any doubts that he has...
如果你能去向他解釋 那么所有疑慮都...
I'm needed here.
這里需要我
To protect him.
來保護他
To persuade the king.
來說服國王
He likes me, George.
他仍喜歡我的 喬治
I feel it.
我能感受的到
And when I have his ear, the cardinal will be recalled.
當他能聽進我的話 主教就會被召回
I promise you.
我保證
What if he dies?
如果他不幸去世怎么辦?
What if he falls off his horse and breaks his neck?
如果他摔下馬脖子折了怎么辦?
Few years ago, this fella here, charged the king in the lists,
幾年前 一個負責國王的飲食起居的小伙
runs his lance into the king's headpiece...bam...
把長矛向國王的頭盔刺去...砰...
lance shatters, an inch, just an inch, from his eye.
長矛在離眼睛一英寸的地方碎掉了
Year later, king's out with his hawk,
一年后 國王帶著他的獵鷹外出
comes to a ditch, drives a pole in to help him cross.
經過一處溝渠時 撐了一根桿渡渠
Damn thing breaks and there he is,
走一半那該死的桿子斷了
face down in a foot of mud, drowning.
他就臉朝下陷進泥潭中 差點淹死
If a servant hadn't pulled him out, who would reign, then?
要不是一個仆人救了他 那現在執政的會是誰呢?
He has one child born in wedlock.
他有一個嫡出的孩子
- What, Mary? The talking shrimp?   - Well, she'll grow up.
- 誰 瑪麗么 那個小蝦米?  - 她總會長大的
We're still waiting. Head's the size of my fingernail.
我們還需等待 她的頭還只有我指甲這么大
And a woman on the English throne flies in the face of nature.
一個女人戴上國王王冠可不是自然而然的事
A woman can't lead an army.
何況女人無法指揮軍隊
Her grandmother did.
她祖母就這么干過
Cromwell what are you doing
克倫威爾 你在干什么
listening to the conversations of gentlemen?
偷聽紳士間的談話嗎
The servant who dragged the king out of the ditch.
那個把國王從泥沼里救出來的仆人
What was his name?
是誰?
Master Cromwell likes to hear of the deeds of those of low birth.
克倫威爾學士總喜歡打聽這些下等人的事哦
His name was Edmund Mody.
他叫 愛德蒙 莫迪
"Muddy" more like! Haha!
聽著怎么像"爛泥巴"...哈！
You've a good eye.
眼力過人嘛
A good arm.
臂力也不錯
Well, at this distance...
這個距離...我還可以應付...
We have a match every Sunday, my household.
我家里面 每周天都會比賽
We meet up with our fellow guildsmen,
我們和公會成員們碰面
and we destroy the butchers and the grocers!
然后去肉店和雜貨店里搞破壞
What if I came down with you one week?
不如下次我跟你同去如何
In disguise?
只是微服出游?
A king should show himself sometimes, don't you think?
國王是需要時不時炫耀一下自己的能力的 你覺得呢
I could shoot for you!
我可以輪替你出場比試射箭
Well, well, we'd win for sure!
那...那我們肯定會贏的
Wolsey told me once that you had a loathing of those in religious life?
沃爾西曾告訴過我你貌似很厭惡宗教生活
That's why he found you so diligent
這是為什么他覺得你對修道院的監察
in your inspection of the monasteries?
如此孜孜不倦的原因嗎
That was not the reason.
不是那個原因
- May I speak?  - God, I wish someone would!
- 我能說兩句么? - 老天 真是求之不得
If you ask me about the monks,
如果你問我對修道士的看法
I speak from experience, not prejudice,
我會說說我的經驗之談 而不是偏見
and my experiences have largely been one of corruption and waste.
而我的過往經歷來看 他們都腐敗且浪費
I've seen monks who live like great lords
我親眼見他們過得像勛爵大人
on the offerings of the poor,
吃著窮人們的救濟糧
take children in,
不停接收新的孩子
and rather than educating them as they promise,
但卻不像承諾般一樣給他們優良教育
use them as servants. For hundreds of years, the monks have written
把孩子們當作仆人 幾千年來 修道士們已經在歷史中
what we take to be our history.
記載了我們被奪去的東西
I think they've suppressed our true history,
但他們卻只是阻礙了真實的歷史進程
and written one which is favourable to Rome.
只攥寫羅馬教廷希望看的篇章
I could make good use of the money
他們每年進貢給教廷的錢
that flows from them to Rome each year.
要是給我 肯定能派上大用處
King Francois is richer than I am.
弗朗斯瓦國王比我富裕的多
He taxes his subjects as he pleases.
他可以隨意收稅
I have to call parliament or there are riots.
而我卻要召集議會來征求意見 否則就會有暴動
Well, sir, with respect, Francois likes war too much
恕我直言 陛下 弗朗斯瓦太嗜戰
and trade too little.
而無視了貿易的重要性
There are more taxes to be raised when trade is good.
若貿易順利的話 將能征得更多的稅收
And if taxes are resisted, even by the Church
而即使有教會的教令 拒絕納稅
other ways can be found.
我們也能有其他的解決辦法
All right.
好吧
Sit down with my lawyers to discuss it.
有時間來跟我的律師們坐下來談談吧
Begin with the monasteries.
從修道院開始
Some say that I should consider my marriage dissolved
一些人說我應該考慮解除婚姻關系
and I should remarry as I please. And soon.
然后我就能盡快娶我真正想要的女人了
- But there are others who say... - I am one of the others.
- 但還有另一幫人說...  - 我就是那幫人中的一個
Dear Christ, I shall be unmanned by it!
我的天 我不會因這些閑言碎語而怯懦的！
How long am I supposed to wait?!
我還有等多久?!
Anne says she'll leave me.
安妮說她要離我而去
Says there are other men.
說她已經有了別的男人
Says she's wasting her youth.
說她現在這樣是在浪費她的青春
Open up!
開門！
It's the king's men. Open up!
我是國王的人 開門！
What is it? Is it an arrest?
發生什么事了 是來抓我們的么
- Good morning, William Brereton. - I'm here if you need me.
- 早上好 威廉 布里爾頓   - 隨時待命
Are you up early, or down late, sir? Take the girls to bed.
您這是早起還是晚睡 先生? 你帶孩子們去睡覺
Come, girls.
走吧 孩子們
The king is at Greenwich. You're to come now.
國王在格林威治 你得現在過去一趟
Well, then, everybody, back to bed.
那所有人都上床睡覺去吧
The king wouldn't invite me to Greenwich in order to arrest me.
國王請我去格林威治 就肯定不是為了抓我
It doesn't happen that way.
逮捕也不是這么個逮捕法
What does he want me for?
他找我要做什么?
I really can't enlighten you.
恕不奉告
Harry Norris.
哈利 諾里斯
Master Cromwell, we do meet under the strangest circumstances.
克倫威爾大人 我們總在奇怪的狀況下見面
You, only, to come in.
你一個人跟我進去
He's waiting.
他在等你
You stay here.
你待在這
My dead brother came to me.
我死去的哥哥來找我了
How did he look?
他看起來還好嗎
As I remember him. But he was pale.
就像記憶中的那樣 不過臉色慘白
And thin.
骨瘦如柴
There was a white fire around him.
而且有一團白色冥火圍繞著他
He died in Ludlow, in winter.
他逝于勒德落 正值寒冬
The roads were impenetrable.
當時道路不通
They had to put his coffin on an ox cart.
只能把他的棺材放在牛車上
I never saw him dead.
我從沒有機會瞻仰他的遺容
Until tonight.
直到今晚
The dead don't come back to complain of their burial.
死去之人不會托夢回來抱怨葬禮的
He was so sad.
他很悲傷
He's come back to make me ashamed.
他回來是為了讓我羞愧
For taking his kingdom.
搶了他的王座
Using his wife.
還利用他的妻子
If Your majesty's brother died before he could reign...
如果陛下的哥哥在繼位之前就去世了
.. then that was God's will.
..那便是天意如此
And as for your supposed marriage,
至于您的婚姻
we all know that that was clean,contrary to the scriptures.
我們都知道是清白的 雖違悖圣經
But with God,
但上帝有靈
- there's mercy enough... - Not for me!
- 已足夠仁慈了... - 那又不是對我仁慈!
When I come to my judgment,
每當我自己做出判斷的時候
he will plead against me.
他就會來反駁我
He has come to make me ashamed...
他現在回來是想讓我難堪...
.. and I alone must bear it.
...我卻孤身一人 默默忍受
I...
我...
I alone.
我孤身一人
Did your brother speak to you?
您哥哥跟你談了什么
Make any sign?
有什么暗示嗎
No.
沒有
Then you have read into his face something that wasn't there.
那你就是過度揣測你哥哥的想法了
Listen to me.
聽著
You know what's written on Arthur's tomb?
你知道亞瑟王的墓碑上刻著什么嗎
"Rex quondam rexque futurus."
(拉丁語)
"King once, and king to be."
"一朝為王 永世為王"
Your father made it sure.He came back from exile,
你的父親做到了這句話 他從流放歸來
claimed his ancient right.
奪回了失去的權力
But it's not enough to claim a country, you have to hold it.
但這王位并不穩當 您得掌控住它
It has to be made secure,in every generation.
并將它世代傳承下去
If your brother comes back and seems to say
如果您哥哥回來好像是在責怪你
that you have taken his kingdom, taken his place,
奪了他的王國 他的王位
it's because he wants YOU to become the king he would have been.
那是因為他想讓您成為他曾想登上的王位
He can't fulfil the prophecy,
他不能世代傳承王位
a prince come out of Wales,
因為他是威爾士出身的王子
but he wills you to do it.
但他希望您能繼承王位
But why does he come back now?
那他現在為什么又回來了?
I have been king for 20 years.
我都當了20年國王
Because now is the vital time.
因為現在是關鍵時期
Now is the time for you to become the king you should be,
現在是時候 您表現出王霸之氣
the sole and supreme head of your kingdom.
表現出唯吾獨尊的上位者的氣勢
Ask Anne.
問問安妮
She'll say the same.
她也會這么說
She does.
確實如此
She says we should not bow to Rome.
她說我們不應臣服于羅馬
And if your father should come to you in your dream,
如果您父親也向您托夢
you take it the same way as you take this one.
您也要這樣想
They come to strengthen your hand.
他們是來輔佐您的
I see.
我懂了
I understand it all now.
真的都懂了
I knew who to send for.
我知道派誰去了
I always do.
我一直都該知道的
What happened?
發生什么事了
The king had a dream.
國王做了個夢
A dream?
做夢?
He got us out of bed for a dream?
他半夜把我們叫醒 就因為一個夢?
Oh, believe me, he gets one out of bed for far less than that.
相信我 他還有別的原因的
Was it a bad dream?
是個噩夢嗎
"Was it a bad dream?"
"是噩夢嗎"
He thought it was.
他本來是這么認為的
It isn't now.
但現在不是了
Your children love you.
你的孩子們很愛你
We can't do without the man in charge.
沒有這個帶頭人 我們也都做不成事的
Dr Cranmer, tell the Lady Anne
克雷默先生 告訴安娜夫人
we did a good night's work for her tonight.
我們今晚替她辦了件大好事
Quietly now.
保持安靜
Don't wake the house a second time.
別又把大家吵醒了
Well done.
很好
Safe?
你沒事吧
Mm.
嗯
I thought...
我還以為...
What?
什么?
I thought it was going to be a reckoning.
我還以為要來清算了
A reckoning?
清算什么
For what?
為了什么
I don't know. All the things.
不知道 所有的這一切吧
The paintings, the books and lutes, and I don't know what.
這些畫 書 魯特琴 還有些不認識的東西
The things we have now.
我們現在所擁有的一切
You, sir, are a Roman pauper!
先生你真是個羅馬乞丐!
Sir, you are a fat Fleming,
先生你真是個佛萊芒大胖子
and spread butter on your bread.
面包上還抹著黃油
Well, sir, may your offspring eat snails.
先生 愿您的后代都吃蝸牛
Call Me Risley!
叫我里斯利！
You look fit to be painted, Master Wriothesley! What are you about?
給你畫下來應該很不錯 里奧謝思利學士！你在這干嘛
Waiting on the children. They're in high spirits this morning.
等孩子們 他們今早很有興致呢
La la la la, la la la...
啦啦啦啦...啦啦啦...
What's that?
哼的那是什么調
It's a tune from my days in Italy.
以前我在意大利的時候學的小曲
I remember...
我還記得...
He never tells stories about himself.
他從不說他自己的故事
Well, well... I, erm...
好吧...我...呃...
When I was in Italy, me and the...
在意大利的時候 我和...
.. me and the Portinari boys,
我和那些波爾蒂納里家的男孩們
the Portinari boys,
波爾蒂納里家的男孩們
we had a statue made,
我們做了個雕像
a little smirking god with wings.
揮舞著翅膀傻笑的上帝小雕像
We beat it with hammers and chains,hired a muleteer and drove it to Rome
我們用錘子和鏈條敲打它 還雇了個騾夫 把雕像運到羅馬
and sold it to a cardinal as an antique from the reign of Augustus.
還冒充是奧古斯都時期的古董 賣給了一個紅衣大主教
I remember...
我還記得...
he. he had tears in his eyes when he paid us.
當他付我們錢時 眼里還噙著淚水
And when the Portinari boys went back to Florence
當波爾蒂納里家的男孩們回佛羅倫薩時
they were staggering under the weight of their purses.
他們因為錢袋太重 路都走不穩了
- What did you do?  - What?
- 那你做了什么  - 什么
Took my cut, and stayed on to sell the mules, what do you think?
分了我那份錢 留下來接著賣拖鞋 不然呢
(Italian) ? Scaramella va alla guerra ?
（意大利語）? Scaramella會有戰爭 ?
(Italian) ? Colla lancia et la rotella ?
（意大利語）? 長矛啊 武器啊 ?
We hadn't finished dinner.
我們還未用完晚餐
They came in,
他們就來了
they'd taken the keys from the porter.
他們從門房那里拿了鑰匙
They'd already set sentries on the stairs.
他們已經在樓梯口設了哨兵
Who was it?
是誰
Harry Percy.
哈利 珀西
He was shaking.
他渾身發抖
I thought, "Why send him? Why Harry Percy?"'
我就想 "為什么要派他 為什么是哈利 珀西"'
Then I thought...
然后我想起...
Lady Anne, you remember,
安妮夫人 你還記得嗎
she was just a girl.
她那時只是個女孩
She wanted to marry him.
她想嫁給他
The cardinal stopped it.
紅衣主教閣下卻阻止了
Revenge.
這是在復仇
She waited her time.
她已經等候多時了
Harry,
哈利
if I'd known, I would have waited dinner for you.
要是知道你來 我會等你共進晚餐的
I fear we've almost finished the fish.
貌似魚都快吃光了
- Shall I pray for a miracle?   - My lord, I arrest you for high treason.
- 我要祈禱奇跡發生嗎  - 大人，我以叛國罪逮捕你
Your warrant?
逮捕令呢
There are items in my instructions you may not see.
我自有王命在身 但非你可看
Well, if you won't show it,
如若你不把它展示出來
I won't surrender to you.
恐怕我是不會屈服的
So...
所以...
here's a state of affairs!
就是這么個情況
Come, George.
走吧 喬治
Look at me, George.
看著我 喬治
I'm not afraid of any man alive.
我不懼怕任何生者
Um...
呃...
Er...
恩...
They took us from the house, rode south.
他們把我們從房子里帶走 向南走
There were crowds waiting to see him, holding candles.
有一群人在等著見他 舉著蠟燭
We thought they'd disperse, but they just stood all night in the road.
我們以為他們會散去 但他們整晚都站在路中央
He stopped eating.
他絕食了
Why?
為什么
I don't know.
我不知道
Some said... some said he wanted to destroy himself.
有人說...有人說他想毀滅自己
It all happened so fast.
一切發生的太快了
And then Kingston came.
之后金斯頓來了
I had to tell him, Thomas.
我不得不告訴他 托馬斯
I had to tell our lord that the Constable of the Tower
我不得不告訴我們大人 象牙塔的那個治安官
had come to fetch him.
已經來帶走他了
He just kept saying "William Kingston?"
他只是重復問道"威廉 金斯頓?"
over and over, as if he couldn't believe it.
一遍又一遍 好像他不敢相信
By the time we reached Leicester
我們抵達萊斯特時
he was too ill to stand.
他虛弱的站都站不住
He voided black blood.
咳出了黑色的血
I thought... poison...
我認為...是有人下毒...
Thomas...
托馬斯...
He's coming, my lord.
他馬上來了 大人
Where... where is he?
他在哪兒?
You know Cromwell, my lord.
你知道克倫威爾的 大人
If he says he'll come, he'll be here.
他說會來 就一定會來的
'I'm sorry, Thomas.'
"對不起 托馬斯"
'He died the next day.'
"他第二天就去世了"
They...
他們...
They gave him
他們給了他
a coffin of plain boards.
一個紙板糊起來的棺材
And the city officials came to view his body
市里的官員來查驗了他的尸體
so there couldn't be any false rumours that he'd escaped to France.
來破除說他已經逃亡法國的謠言
They... they made jokes.
他們...他們還嘲笑他
They made jokes about his low birth!
嘲笑他卑微的出身
Come, Wolsey! We're fetching you to Hell,
來 沃爾西 我們接你下地獄
where our master, Beelzebub,
我們的魔王大人
is expecting you to supper!
正盼著和你共進晚餐
Beelzebub would have you joint his venison.
魔王愿和你共享野味
He's heard of your skill as a butcher!
他聽說您可是一個屠夫的兒子
'"I swear to be a true and faithful councillor..."'
"我發誓成為皇家樞密院的議員..."
"to the King's Majesty as one of His Highness's Privy Council."
"忠誠無二的效忠國王陛下"
I swear to be a true and faithful councillor
我發誓成為皇家樞密院的議員
to the King's Majesty as one of His Highness's Privy Council.
忠誠無二的效忠國王陛下
"I shall not know or understand of any manner thing to be attempted,
"我不會參與或做出任何"
"done, or spoken against His Majesty's person..."
"違抗或頂撞國王陛下的事情"
I shall not know or understand of any manner thing
我不會參與或做出任何
to be attempted, done, or spoken against His Majesty's person.
違抗或頂撞國王陛下的事情
'"I swear to uphold the king's authorities.
"我立誓維護國王的威望"
'"I swear to uphold the king's jurisdictions..."
"我立誓維護國王的統治..."
'I swear to uphold the king's authorities.
我立誓維護國王的威望
'I swear to uphold the king's jurisdictions.
我立誓維護國王的統治
'"I swear to uphold the king's heirs and lawful successors."'
"我立誓擁護國王的子嗣及法定繼承人"
I swear to uphold the king's heirs and lawful successors.
我立誓擁護國王的子嗣及法定繼承人
I knelt by his body...
我跪在他身側...
.. and I wept
為他而哭泣
and I prayed to God to send vengeance upon them all!
也向上帝祈禱 復仇降臨到他們每人身上
There's no need to trouble God, George.
不必勞煩上帝 喬治
I'll take it in hand.
我將親手復仇